Preliminary Guide to the Nahanni Productions Archive
Yale University Arts Library
Nahanni Productions archive
1964-2013
1980-2010
AOB 125
Yale University Arts Library
14
(25 boxes)
The archive contains materials that document the photography and bookworks by Pat and Rosemarie Keough, who are the proprietors of Nahanni Productions. The archive includes process materials relating to individual book projects as well as correspondence and other research materials.
Keough, Pat, 1945-
Keough, Rosemarie, 1959-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Pat and Rosemarie Keough, 2013, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Curatorial permission required.
Biographical / Historical
Pat and Rosemarie Keough are fine art photographers and private press publishers. Much of their photographic work focuses on environmental and social causes. As proprietors of Nahanni Productions Inc., the Keoughs oversee every element of book production, as exemplified by their limited edition Explorer Series.
Scope and Contents
The archive contains materials that document the photography and bookworks by Pat and Rosemarie Keough, including process materials relating to individual book projects as well as correspondence and other research and promotional materials.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Biographical. II. Correspondence. III. Publicity. IV. Book Projects. V. Additional Research Materials.
Private press books; Nature photography; Correspondence; Promotional materials; Dummies (Printed matter)
- Biographical, 1964-1981; Series I; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains examples of Rosemarie's early books, such as journals and other childhood ephemera.
  - Adventures and Experiences of Rosemarie E. Czirfusz, May 1981, 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Collection of Good Times that occurred during the Fall of 1981 and during the time that followed, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Further Adventures of Rosemarie Czirfusz, June 1981, 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rosemarie's kindergarten efforts, 1964-1965, 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1980-2001; Series II; 2
  Arrangement
  Organized by type of correspondent: General, Fans, Printers/Publishers.
  Series II contains correspondence with various individuals and institutions, such as printers and publishers, as well as letters from fans.
  - General, 1981-2001; 10
    - Bateman, Robert - famed Canadian wildlife artist, 1981-2000; 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Canadian Geographic Magazine and Gift Catalog, 1986-1994; 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes correspondence as well as an agreement.
    - Royal Canadian Geographic Society, 1986; 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Victor Emanuel Nature Tours (VENT)—Ref: Lords of Antarctic's publicity tour, 2001; 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence as well as fliers.
    - Monk, Lorraine, 1986-1988; 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Patterson, Dennis, 1989; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Tilly, Alex, 1986-1992; 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Trueman, Peter, 1988-1991; 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Western Canada Wilderness Committee WC2, 1988-1995; 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Nahanni Portfolio, 1986-1988; 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes Keoughs' letters sent to sponsors.
  - Fan Letters, 1980-2000; 4
    - 1980s-1990, 1980-1990; 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1980s-1990s, 1988-1993; 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1990s-2000, 1992-2000; 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1990s-2000, 1991-2000; 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Printers/Publishers, 1980-1996; 4
    - Jack Stoddart Publishing Co., 1980-1992; 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Jack Stoddart Publishing Co., 1987-1996; 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Includes contracts.
    - Toppan Printing: Keough titles, 1989-1995; 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Toppan Printing: Beautiful Arnprior, 1988-1993; 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Includes quote, contract, and shipping information.
- Publicity, 1984-2012; Series III; 3
  Series III includes publicity materials such as newspaper and magazine articles.
  Arranged roughly in reverse chronological order. Articles pertaining to the works Labyrinth Sublime and Antarctica are listed separately at the end of the series.
  - Awards articles pre-1984, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Newspapers and duplicates slides, 1985; 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 2012 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Includes articles published in The Explorers Journal and Outdoor Photography Canada.
  - 2009 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Includes articles published in Architectural Digest.
  - 2008 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Includes articles published in American Bibliophilic Societies.
  - 2007 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Includes articles published in American Bibliophilic Societies, Digital Photographer (Ukrainian edition), Photo Mozaik.
  - 2006 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Includes articles published in American Bibliophilic Societies, Patek Philippe (English edition), Photo Ed, Polar Priorities, Sideroads of Halton Hills.
  - 2005 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Includes articles published in The Explorers Journal, Geographical, Publish: Design, Works, Print (journal title translated from Russian), and Western Living.
  - 2004 Magazines (1 of 3), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Includes articles published in Aqua, American Printer, Fine Books & Collections (Nov.-Dec. 2004), Photo District News, Saturday Night.
  - 2004 Magazines (2 of 3), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Includes articles published in Bucher, Geographical, Outpost, Smithsonian.
  - 2004 Magazines (3 of 3), 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Includes articles published in Departures, Foto Magazin, I.D., Tabellae Ansatae, Vanity Fair.
  - 2003 Magazines (1 of 3), 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Includes articles published in Amphora, The Explorers Journal, InTouch, A Peak Inside, Printing Impressions.
  - 2003 Magazines (2 of 3), 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Includes articles published in Book tech Magazine, Millionaire, Print Media, The Seventh Continent, Time, Time for Kids.
  - 2003 Magazines (3 of 3), 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 36)
    Includes articles published in Camera Arts, The Economist, Entertainment Weekly, Jets Go, The Lucie Awards.
  - 2002 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 37)
    Includes articles published in The Alcuin Society, Amphora, Canadian Antarctic Research Network (vol. 14), Forbes, Forbes Global, The Heron, Maclean's.
  - 1998 Magazines, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 38)
    Includes articles published in In Touch.
  - Labyrinth Sublime: 2012 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Labyrinth Sublime: 2011 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Antarctica: 2007 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Antarctica: 2006 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Antarctica: 2005 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Antarctica: 2004 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Antarctica: 2003 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Antarctica: 2002 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Antarctica: 2001 Newspaper articles, 1 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Book Projects, 1984-2013; Series IV; 10
  Materials are generally grouped by project title.
  Series IV contains process materials, marketing materials, and correspondence related to various book projects by Pat and Rosemarie Keough / Nahanni Productions. These projects include: Nahanni Portfolio, The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio, Beautiful Arnprior, Ottawa Valley Portfolio, Wild and Beautiful Sable Island, The Beauty of Renfrew and Area, Nova Scotia Portfolio, Antarctica, and Labyrinth Sublime.
  Individual catalog records for the Keoughs' published works can also be found in Orbis.
  - Nahanni Portfolio: specifications, 1988; 1 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Nahanni Portfolio: permissions, 1987; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 49)
    Includes permissions to quote from books and image use; model release and book The Dangerous River.
  - Nahanni Portfolio: Northwest Territories, 1989-1993; 1 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Includes contract and image use – GNWT.
  - Nahanni Portfolio: publicity, 1988; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Nahanni Portfolio: publicity, 1988-1993; 1 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Includes Outdoor Photographer Magazine and Photo Life Magazine.
  - Nahanni Portfolio: publicity, 1993; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Includes Explore Magazine.
  - Nahanni National Park Reserve: expansion, 1995-2013; 1 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Nahanni Portfolio, 1991; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Includes Bateman Calendars 1991 – Keough images.
  - Nahanni Portfolio, 1989-1990; 1 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    Includes materials related to Canadian Helicopters (sponsor).
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: design notes, 1990; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 57)
    Includes book design notes and computer layout.
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: production, 1989-1990; 1 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    Includes costs and production schedule.
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: printing, 1989-1992; 1 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    Includes Toppan Printing quote invoice.
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: picture credits, 1989-1990; 1 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    Includes letters and other documents pertaining to picture credits.
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: publicity, 1990-1993; 1 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    Includes publicity materials from INC. Media.
  - The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio: others' projects, 1991-1994; 1 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    Includes materials about others' projects in which the Keoughs assisted.
  - Beautiful Arnprior, 1992-1993; 1 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    Includes solicitation letter and responses, orders.
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio: stamp, 1992; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 64)
    Includes materials related to a stamp for Canada Post.
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio: financial analysis, 1984-1985; 1 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio: French translation, 1 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio: publicity, 1986-1987; 1 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio: awards and letters, 1987-1989; 1 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Ottawa Valley Portfolio and The Niagara Escarpment: A Portfolio, 1 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    Includes pre-publication materials.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island: printing, 1993; 1 (Box 9, Folder 70)
    Includes Toppan printing quote.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island: distribution, 1993-2005; 1 (Box 9, Folder 71)
    Includes distribution agreement and letters from Nimbus.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island: consignment and payments, 1994-2005; 1 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    Includes Nimbus consignment records and payments from, dated 1998-2005, as well as information about the book selling out, dated June 2005.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island: publicity, 1993-1999; 1 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    Includes publicity and information about the park.
  - Beautiful Renfrew: quotes, 1994; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 74)
    Includes quotes printed by Friesens.
  - Beautiful Renfrew and Seniors Home Support, 1997-1998; 1 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Nova Scotia Portfolio, 1989-1992; 1 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island, 1993-1995; 1 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    Includes process materials such as instructions for printers.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island, 1993; 1 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    Includes ink proofs from printers with comments from Keoughs.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island, 1992; 1 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    Includes original maps, tracing of frontispiece, reproduction of vintage photos used.
  - Wild and Beautiful Sable Island, 1993; 1 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    Includes folded, gathered, and trimmed signatures after printing entire book, but before binding (last signature missing).
  - Beautiful Arnprior: publicity, 1992-1993; 1 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Beautiful Arnprior: process materials, 1992; 1 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    Includes an incomplete set of folded and gathered signatures.
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 1, 1 (Box 11)
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 2, 1 (Box 11)
  - Antarctica: Blue Binder, 1 (Box 11)
    Proofreaders included: ornithologists, glaciologist, Antarctica historians, biologists, Antarctica tourism & expeditions experts, artists, and friends.
  - Antarctica: Blue Binder: Prime Production A, 1 (Box 12)
    Includes all correspondence and invoice copies (such as Hemlock Printers, Felton Bookbinding, Hewits – leather) and additional binding materials.
  - Antarctica: Blue Binder: Secondary Production, 1 (Box 12)
    Includes notes and letters with firms the Keoughs did not select to work with on Antarctica.
  - Antarctica: Blue Binder: Secondary Tour Operators & Expeditions, 1 (Box 12)
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 3, 1 (Box 13)
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 4, 1 (Box 13)
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 5, 1 (Box 13)
  - Antarctica: Red Binder: Marketing book 6, 1 (Box 14)
  - Antarctica & Labyrinth Sublime: Red Binder: Awards, 1 (Box 14)
    Note: actual awards and/or facsimiles.
  - Antarctica: White binder: Marketing, 2004; 1 (Box 14)
    Includes a report dated September 2004.
  - The Nahanni Portfolio: Blue binder: Design notes, 1 (Box 14)
  - Marketing information, 3 (Box 15, Folder 83-85)
    Includes works by other publishers, which were researched and monitored by the Keoughs.
  - Antarctica & Labyrinth Sublime, 1 (Box 15, Folder 86)
    Includes sample books and leather head- and tailband materials from the following: J. Hewit & Sons Ltd.; Tanners and Leather Dressers; Bowden's Book Headbands; Daniel/Prestige velvet; Harmatan Leather Ltd.
  - Beautiful Arnprior: dummy book - Toppan, 1992; 1 (Box 15, Folder 87)
  - Niagara Escarpment: dummy book, 1989; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 88)
  - Antarctica: exercise book, 2001; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 89)
    Includes ideas for the text Antarctica, transcribed notes from BBC's "Life in the Freezer," front cover sketches, and die ideas.
  - Antarctica: die instructions, 1 (Box 16, Folder 90)
  - Antarctica: front cover, 1 (Box 16, Folder 91)
    Includes two die tests of engraving styles and the Antarctica front cover die (design by P&R Keough, engraving by Frank Bonigut Engraving Limited).
  - Antarctica prototypes, 9
    These materials document the Keoughs' search for a strong binding structure suitable for their weighty, limited edition Explorer Series project. The Keoughs solicited prototypes from the following bookbinders: Harcourt Bindery in Boston, MA; Roswell Bookbinding in Phoenix, AZ; and Felton Bookbinding in Georgetown, Ontario. The Keoughs ultimately worked with Keith Felton, who developed a custom binding for Antarctica by combining the techniques of a classic European leather binding and a split-board ledger binding.
    In addition to the iterative prototypes or "dummies" for Antarctica, each box contains typewritten specifications and subsequent evaluations by the Keoughs. For more detailed Antarctica production notes, see also Box 12.
    - Harcourt #1 (Box 17)
    - Harcourt #2 (Box 18)
    - Roswell #1 (Box 19)
    - Roswell #2 (Box 20)
    - Felton #1 (Box 21)
    - Felton #1 textblock (Box 22)
    - Felton #2 (Box 23)
    - Felton #3 (Box 24)
    - Felton #4 leather case (Box 25)
      This is an actual case for Antarctica, which shows the cover design as well as the splits in the interior boards.
- Additional Research Materials, 1988-1998; Series V; 2
  - Keough books: project and ideas, 1988-1994; 1 (Box 16, Folder 92)
    Includes documents related to unrealized book projects.
  - Salt Spring Island Portfolio, 1998; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 93)
    Includes documents related to the beginnings of the Explorer Series concept.